Guide to the Graham Cook Lumber Company Records, 1882-1915 AIS.1998.12
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Graham Cook Lumber Company Records
1882-1915
1893-1913
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Graham Cook Lumber Company
AIS.1998.12
3.38 Linear Feet (5 boxes)
This collection contains manuscript and typewritten correspondence, bills, orders, inventories, and receipts of the Graham Cook Lumber Company, Armstrong County, Pennsylvania, 1882-1915.
History
George Graham, of Brady's Bend, Pennsylvania, first entered into the lumber business with Judge A. Cook of Cooksburg in 1870. In 1874 they moved Graham, Forcht Company to East Brady, Armstrong Co., Pa. to increase the scale of their planing mill and lumber sales. The company specialized in the purchase and sale of a wide variety of rough and ready lumber, with most of its business conducted in western and central Pennsylvania. In 1902, sometime after renaming the business Graham Cook, George Graham sold his interest in the company to his son, Newton Ellsworth Graham. Newton Graham had previously served as the founder, editor, and publisher of the East Brady Review, a local newspaper, and the first president of the People's National Bank of East Brady. In 1902 Newton Graham bought out the Cook interests in the lumber company and organized the Graham Lumber Company.
Scope and Content Notes
This collection is almost entirely comprised of manuscript and typewritten correspondence, bills, orders, inventories, and receipts. The content of the letters revolve around business matters (i.e., the sale and transportation of lumber). The correspondence also reflects dealings with railroad companies and other firms participating in the region's industrial expansion (i.e.. steel, coal, manufacturing, etc.). The majority of business transactions occurred within central and western Pennsylvania, but correspondents range all the way to Mississippi and the Puget Sound. The bulk of the collection dates from 1893-1900, 1904, and 1913 and is organized in chronological order. Letters are also in chronological order within each folder.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Acquired from Carmen Valentino, Philadelphia, Pa., March 5, 1998.
Previous Citation
Graham Cook Lumber Company Records, 1882-1915, AIS.1998.12, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Lumber-yards -- Pennsylvania; Lumber trade -- Pennsylvania -- History; Business and Industry; Graham Cook Lumber Company -- Archives; Graham, George; Graham, Newton E.
- 1882 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- 1891 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- 1892 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- 1893 (Box 1, Folder 4-8)
- 1894 (Box 1, Folder 9-21)
- 1895 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- 1896 (Box 2, Folder 23-35)
- 1897 (Box 2, Folder 36)
- 1898 (Box 2, Folder 37-39)
- 1898 (Box 3, Folder 40-48)
- 1899 (Box 3, Folder 49-56)
- 1899 (Box 4, Folder 57-61)
- 1900 (Box 4, Folder 62-68)
- 1901 (Box 4, Folder 69)
- 1903 (Box 4, Folder 70)
- 1904 (Box 4, Folder 71-77)
- 1904 (Box 5, Folder 78-83)
- 1905 (Box 5, Folder 84)
- 1906 (Box 5, Folder 85)
- 1911 (Box 5, Folder 86)
- 1912 (Box 5, Folder 87-88)
- 1913 (Box 5, Folder 89-100)
- 1915 (Box 5, Folder 101)
- Miscellaneous, no date (Box 5, Folder 102)